Chris: Software maintenance is a key part
of the software development life cycle.
Its purpose is to modify and continuously
update software applications to eliminate all
possible errors, malfunctions, to improve work
efficiency and better system performance and
ensure the software meets customer’s needs.
Leah: Software developers don’t have the luxury
of launching a product and then forgetting
about it, they constantly need to be on the
lookout to both correct and improve their
software to remain competitive and relevant.
Developing a piece of software can take a
couple of years but maintenance is ongoing
for the lifetime of the product and can
last up to 20 years and sometimes even more.
Let’s look at the four main
types of software maintenance.
Chris: Corrective maintenance
‘Corrective software maintenance’ is the typical,
classic form of maintenance, if something goes
wrong and then a solution is developed to fix it.
Corrective software maintenance is necessary
when a piece of software shows faults and
errors, or perhaps there is a compatibility issue
with another piece of newly released software.
These can have a widespread impact
on functionality and therefore must
be addressed as quickly as possible.
Leah: Frequently software developers can address
issues that require ‘corrective maintenance’
due to error or bug reports that users send in.
If a company can recognize and take care
of faults before users discover them, then
this is an added advantage that will make
a company seem more reputable and reliable
Chris: Adaptive maintenance
Technology is constantly changing, and it is
of critical importance that software is able
to keep up with these changes and ‘Adaptive
maintenance’ takes this into consideration.
There may be a new version of an operating
system launched or a new type of processor
that will affect how the software performs.
Sometimes, adaptive software maintenance reflects
organizational policies or rules as well.
Updating services, making modifications to
vendors, or changing payment processors can
all necessitate adaptive software maintenance.
Leah: A typical example is the infamous Y2K
bug of 1999, where companies believed their
software would no longer function as the
date shifted from 31/12/1999 to 1/1/2000.
In response, developers worked to prepare
their software in anticipation of Y2K problems.
If they had failed to do so, they
would be dealing with a corrective
maintenance problem on January 1.
Chris: Perfective maintenance
‘Perfective software maintenance’
focuses on features that improve the user
experience through functional enhancements.
It's about improving the system performance
in ways that aren't specifically in
response to a fault or problem, but
instead in response to customer feedback.
Examples are ‘code functionality enhancements’,
‘usability changes’, or ‘speed optimization’,
all of which improve the value of
software and enhance the user experience.
Leah: Preventive Software Maintenance
‘Preventive Software Maintenance’ is
about software changes and adaptations.
These reduce the risk of deterioration,
as software is operated for a long time.
Preventative Software Maintenance
improves maintainability and
stability, through code optimization,
restructuring, and documentation updates.
Examples may include new features to
improve reliability and performance, and
refining software to reduce complexity to
make it easier to maintain and understand.
Chris: As we all know software systems age
and ‘preventive software maintenance’ is about
future-proofing its longevity and efficacy by
implementing good practices for long-term gain.